<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title> Knot Theory</title>
    <description>Course Page for UNI Math 4159</description>
    <link>http://theronhitchman.github.io/knot-theory/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://theronhitchman.github.io/knot-theory/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>Mirrors and Reverses</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We discussed two new concepts today: the mirror image of a knot, and the reverse
of an oriented knot. We looked at four examples: the trefoil knot \( 3_1 , \)
the figure eight knot \( 4_1 , \) the five-crossing knot \( 5_2 , \) and the eight crossing knot \( 8_{15} . \) You can find
each of these on the site KnotInfo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;for-wednesday&quot;&gt;For Wednesday&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There seem to be two ways of making a mirror image. Given a knot K, you could
make a new knot K’ by changing all of the crossings of K. Or, you could
reflect the knot diagram of K across some line in the plane to get a new knot
K’’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Show that K’ and K’’ are always equivalent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This allows us to speak unabmiguously about the mirror image of a knot. A knot
is called &lt;em&gt;achiral&lt;/em&gt; (or &lt;em&gt;amphichiral&lt;/em&gt;) when it is equivalent to its
mirror image. A knot is called &lt;em&gt;chiral&lt;/em&gt; when it is not equivalent to its mirror
image. I mentioned in class that the trefoil knot is chiral, but proving this is
challenging and will have to wait until we build some tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Show that the figure eight knot \(4_1\) is achiral by drawing a sequence
  of knot diagrams between \(4_1\) and its mirror image with easily understood
  steps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also talked about how a knot can be given a “sense of travel”, called an
&lt;em&gt;orientation&lt;/em&gt;. Each knot has two of these of course. A knot together with a
choice of orientation is called an &lt;em&gt;oriented knot&lt;/em&gt;. If K is an oriented knot,
the knot Kr with the opposite orientation is called the &lt;em&gt;reverse&lt;/em&gt; of K.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we carry the orientations along as we look for equivalent knots, we can talk
about oriented equivalence of oriented knots. Some oriented knots are oriented
equivalent to their reverses, and some aren’t. [See what I did there?] An
oriented knot which is oriented equivalent to its reverse is called
&lt;em&gt;invertible.&lt;/em&gt; Of course, sometimes we just say a knot is invertible when its
two orientations are oriented equivalent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Show that the knot \(8_{15}\) is invertible by finding a sequence of
  oriented knot diagrams between its two orientations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2017 11:05:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://theronhitchman.github.io/knot-theory/2017/01/13/mirrors-and-reverses.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://theronhitchman.github.io/knot-theory/2017/01/13/mirrors-and-reverses.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>First Invariants</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We talked about three geometric invariants of knots today: the &lt;em&gt;crossing
number&lt;/em&gt;, the &lt;em&gt;unknotting number&lt;/em&gt;, and the quality of being &lt;em&gt;alternating&lt;/em&gt;.
It is important to note that the first two are quantitative in nature because
one associates a number to a knot, but the third is qualitative (and binary)
because a knot is either alternating or it isn’t. [see what I did there?]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used the following examples today:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a disguised trefoil,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a trefoil \(3_1\),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the six-crossing knot \(6_3\),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the seven-crossing knot \(7_4\), and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Goeritz’s unknot.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find more about these, and diagrams from the site
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiana.edu/~knotinfo/&quot;&gt;KnotInfo&lt;/a&gt;. Well, for the last one you might
need to do a Google Search.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;for-friday&quot;&gt;For Friday:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Check which of the knots and links from our table is alternating, which
aren’t. [I did it again.]&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Find a sequence of diagrams which helps show that Goeritz’s unknot really is
the unknot.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;update&quot;&gt;UPDATE&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t want to forget that Eric (the charm one) asked a really interesting
question, which brought us to discuss Peter Guthrie Tait and one of his famous
conjectures:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conjecture:&lt;/em&gt; [P.G. Tait, ca. 1880] Any reduced diagram of an alternating
link has the fewest possible crossings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We haven’t talked about what “reduced” means, yet. Don’t worry, we’ll come back
to this later.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2017 11:15:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://theronhitchman.github.io/knot-theory/2017/01/11/first-invariants.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://theronhitchman.github.io/knot-theory/2017/01/11/first-invariants.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Big Questions</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We started by playing with some knots. So far, we have come across these basic
but important ideas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is a knot? How should we represent them on a page?
How could we tell if two links are the same thing?
How could we tell if two links are genuinely different?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The questions there are the basic questions of knot theory, and we will learn
some of what humanity has devised as answers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Wednesday, please try to figure out if each of the pairs of links from our
little table is either the same or different. There are
\[ \binom{15}{2} = 15\times 7 = 105\]
such pairs, so you won’t figure them all out. That’s okay. Do what you can.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2017 11:15:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://theronhitchman.github.io/knot-theory/2017/01/09/big-question.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://theronhitchman.github.io/knot-theory/2017/01/09/big-question.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Welcome</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Welcome to Math 4159/5159 &lt;em&gt;Knot Theory&lt;/em&gt;. This course is new and &lt;em&gt;experimental&lt;/em&gt;.
I am busy making final decisions, and the &lt;a href=&quot;/knot-theory/syllabus/index.html&quot;&gt;syllabus&lt;/a&gt; will get finished before
class begins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, there are a mix of undergraduate and graduate students enrolled.
The main spirit of the course will be the same for all, but I will expect a combination
of (1) better results, and (2) more work from the graduate students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am very excited to get started. See you Monday!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2017 19:30:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://theronhitchman.github.io/knot-theory/2017/01/05/Welcome.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://theronhitchman.github.io/knot-theory/2017/01/05/Welcome.html</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
